<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Open Source Contributions on I break things often and sometimes I manage to fix them</title>
    <link>https://www.julienrouse.com/projects/contributions/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Open Source Contributions on I break things often and sometimes I manage to fix them</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.julienrouse.com/projects/contributions/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>First contribution: cl-string</title>
      <link>https://www.julienrouse.com/projects/contributions/cl-string/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.julienrouse.com/projects/contributions/cl-string/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;First contribution to another project on Github ever! :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was very small, the library was a very small and new library that wanted to groups lots of functionalities pertaining to strings for Common Lisp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creator/maintener asked for help on the lisp subreddit and I gave it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a good way to get my feet wet, a very small project with a responsive maintainer that took the time to explains things to me on how to contribute on Github and such.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tiny contribution to Ocaml&#39;s GC documentation</title>
      <link>https://www.julienrouse.com/projects/contributions/ocaml/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.julienrouse.com/projects/contributions/ocaml/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While looking at an article explaining the new &amp;ldquo;best fit&amp;rdquo; GC strategy for OCaml &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ocamlpro.com/2020/03/23/ocaml-new-best-fit-garbage-collector/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, they had a link toward the source code and I went to see what it looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ocaml/ocaml/blob/trunk/runtime/freelist.c#L882&#34;&gt;Here is the source&lt;/a&gt; I was looking at, and the string documenting the struct did not have the same name for the field in the struct. It&amp;rsquo;s a tiny tiny thing but the kind that feels messy when you read the code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>hugo-resume fix some css</title>
      <link>https://www.julienrouse.com/projects/contributions/hugo-resume/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.julienrouse.com/projects/contributions/hugo-resume/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It feels good to fix the theme I use for the blog, I give back to a tool I will use for some time hopefully :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem was that when looking at blog post with full resolution on my laptop, it displayed nicely. But when viewing it with smartphone resolution, it looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.julienrouse.com/img/contributions_width_overflow.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;blog post with text overflowing&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After some duckduckgoing, I stumbled upon &lt;code&gt;box-sizing: border-box&lt;/code&gt;, an element I have not used before.I went to MDN to see what is was &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/box-sizing&#34;&gt;MDN page on box-sizing&lt;/a&gt;, then looked around if it could be that element tripping me up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But according to that doc, because the CSS used &lt;code&gt;border-box&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;content-box&lt;/code&gt;, my content should have behaved nicely and not overflowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After more time looking around, &lt;a href=&#34;https://stackoverflow.com/a/38892861/3729797&#34;&gt;a StackOverflow response&lt;/a&gt; once again saved the day. When using &lt;code&gt;border-box&lt;/code&gt; on a container, you have to set the width on the inner child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I added &lt;code&gt;width: 100%&lt;/code&gt; on the inner child, and &amp;ldquo;voila&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.julienrouse.com/img/contributions_without_width_overflow.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;blog post with text overflowing&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>	