<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>writing on I break things often. Sometimes I manage to fix them</title>
    <link>https://www.julienrouse.com/tags/writing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in writing on I break things often. Sometimes I manage to fix them</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 07:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.julienrouse.com/tags/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Taking notes</title>
      <link>https://www.julienrouse.com/blog/taking-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.julienrouse.com/blog/taking-notes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I was asked to give recommandation on taking notes and knowledge management tools by colleagues a couple time last year so I&amp;rsquo;m sharing it here too, might be useful for other people.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;taking-notes&#34;&gt;Taking notes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;types-of-note&#34;&gt;Types of note&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your mileage may vary here. Personnaly, I separate my notes in a few categories with a template for each. It clarify the intent of the note and allow me to get started rapidly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TODO: self-explanatory. You have stuff you need to accomplish and you don&amp;rsquo;t want to worget.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;capture&amp;rdquo;: more &amp;ldquo;interesting&amp;rdquo; than TODO list, this is where you can write down ideas, observation etc. At first it might sound silly but then when you are able to link those notes to other notes, you might find out that patterns or new ideas emerge. It takes time to get values from these note, that is why consistency helps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;review&amp;rdquo;/&amp;ldquo;learning&amp;rdquo;: you read a book, you watch a conference, you follow a course&amp;hellip; and you might want to write down something you found interesting about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;troubleshooting&amp;rdquo;/&amp;ldquo;tutorial&amp;rdquo;: steps to accomplish a task. Usually when I&amp;rsquo;m debugging a thorny problem, I write down everything I do and the documentation I read because most of the time I need to go back to those notes later to understand better how to solve it efficiently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also choose to not have any category/template and always start from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tools&#34;&gt;Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;features-i-care-about&#34;&gt;Features I care about&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most important features to me are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not being vendor locked. I want to own my notes and my files: being able to export them, use source control on them, write tooling for it&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bidirectional links (&amp;ldquo;wikilinks&amp;rdquo;): being able to see/navigate from a file to where it is referenced is really useful. It allow to get tools to build a graph of note, links ideas together etc. It&amp;rsquo;s not needed however if you only write down TODO list.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;being able to stay in the text editors I use regularly (Emacs and VSCode right now).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You probably care about another set of feature but this will put in perspective the tools listed below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;tools-i-use&#34;&gt;Tools I use&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/&#34;&gt;org-mode&lt;/a&gt;: Killer feature of Emacs. And you get bidirectional links if you use &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/orgmode/comments/gm8jxj/roamlike_behavior_w_bidirectional_links/&#34;&gt;tags&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/toshism/org-super-links&#34;&gt;org-super-links&lt;/a&gt;. But hard to get started if you don&amp;rsquo;t already use Emacs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[Foam]: Plugin for VSCode. Has everything you need to get started if you are a regular VSCode user.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-tools-im-aware-of&#34;&gt;Other tools I&amp;rsquo;m aware of&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://obsidian.md/&#34;&gt;Obsidian&lt;/a&gt;: has everything you need if you don&amp;rsquo;t want to stay in your text editor. And even then, it probably has plugins to help with that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.orgroam.com/&#34;&gt;org-roam&lt;/a&gt;: org-mode on steroid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://logseq.com/&#34;&gt;Logseq&lt;/a&gt;: Looks promising if you don&amp;rsquo;t care for the Electron app&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://roamresearch.com/&#34;&gt;Roam Research&lt;/a&gt;: one of the best tool, inspired a lot of the others in this list. But not free and vendor locked. I am also biased because the tech stack it uses (Clojure/ClojureScript and Datalog) is fascinating me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dokuwiki.org/&#34;&gt;DokuWiki&lt;/a&gt;: Never tried it myself but it&amp;rsquo;s one of the recommended tool in the Zettelkasten community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-further&#34;&gt;Going further&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get inspiration from a few sources for knowledge management or writing to help you think:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://zettelkasten.de/introduction/&#34;&gt;Zettelkasten&lt;/a&gt; is a very interesting methodology on how to takes note for building knowledge and creating ideas, go check it! There are also a lot of links in the sidebar of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/Zettelkasten/&#34;&gt;Zettelkasten subreddit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gettingthingsdone.com/what-is-gtd/&#34;&gt;Get things done&lt;/a&gt; methodology has some ideas on how to takes note mainly focused on TODO list. Lots of buzzword and commercial BS too so tread carefully. Scott Hanselmans &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hanselman.com/blog/scott-hanselmans-complete-list-of-productivity-tips&#34;&gt;productivity tips&lt;/a&gt; is a good starter for this. Same for his talk &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FS1mnISoG7U&#34;&gt;Scaling Yourself - GOTO 2012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;University of Chicago leadership lab: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vtIzMaLkCaM&#34;&gt;The Craft of Writing Effectively&lt;/a&gt;. Solid resource on the topic of non-fiction writing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;most-important-tip&#34;&gt;Most important tip&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just. Do. It.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s easy to spend too much time procrastinating by comparing the differents tools, how to improve your workflow, how to organize your notes, making template, making shortcut to create specific type of notes&amp;hellip;
But it does not matter. Just write down a few notes regularly. And then only when you have the habits of taking notes you can worry about the details slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My NaNoWriMo of 2020</title>
      <link>https://www.julienrouse.com/blog/my-nanowrimo-in-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.julienrouse.com/blog/my-nanowrimo-in-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-nanowrimo-2020&#34;&gt;My Nanowrimo 2020&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always dreamed to be a writer when I was little. It was my answer to everybody that asked me what I wanted to be when I grow up between middle school until late high school. (It was actually my third career choice, my first dream &amp;ldquo;job&amp;rdquo; was being an Eskimo).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I&amp;rsquo;m a bit far off from that path, but writing slowly for this blog brings me a bit closer to that dream. But I write sporadically and my backlog for new articles is getting full. Getting to it is always the hardest part. So I went on my way to subscribe to &lt;a href=&#34;https://nanowrimo.org/about-nano&#34;&gt;NaNoWriMo&lt;/a&gt;: the National Novel Writing Month!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, I&amp;rsquo;m not writing a novel. But I joined anyway to prepare drafts and articles for this blog. The goal of NaNoWriMo is to write 50000 words during November.
For some people, it usually means drafting a novel, or a series of essays. For me the goal will be to add 50000 words to my blog (at least to write drafts.) And maybe toward the end I&amp;rsquo;ll write a few short stories if I have a good pace to try my hands at that kind of writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help in this journey, you can join a local community of people writing their own things. I joined the one from Montréal (Canada, QC) to have a small community to share my achievements and my hardships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;50000 words in a month is a lot. To give some perspective, since I started this blog in 2018, I wrote around 20000 words and published around 12000 of them. So if I &amp;ldquo;win&amp;rdquo; NaNoWriMo this year, I&amp;rsquo;ll more than double what I did previously in approximately two years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-plan&#34;&gt;The plan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To write that much, I needed a plan. So I started by looking at my backlog of ideas and projects, ordering item, tagging them accordingly. As of today I have around 50 things I want to talk about during NaNoWrimo (and this article is the first one) including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Git and the great value of knowing in depth our tooling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Kush Empire: there were black Pharaoh!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The influence of fencing, the great values of this sport and how doing sport at a very high level translates to the workplace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What I read/listen/watch recently that had a big impact on me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python 3.9 and the PEP about adding macros to Python (as in: Lisp&amp;rsquo;s macro, not C&amp;rsquo;s macro)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reflection on my mistakes and my wins of 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The benefits of being exposed to many programming languages and paradigms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And a lot more hopefully!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also hoping to nourish a habit of writing by pushing me to write every day for a month. For now I intend to write 30 minutes in the morning before work, 30 minutes for my lunch break and 30 minutes or more in the evening. The evening is a bit harder to plan for me but I should be able to at least get a good hour of writing every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;obstacles&#34;&gt;Obstacles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know already that a few obstacles are coming ahead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll have a very busy month at work. We are launching in production a service that has been in the working for more than a year without being seen by a user. (I know how much of a great idea this is&amp;hellip;) But in a way, I think doing NaNoWriMo will help me reset my brain from work and that will be a good time to do it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to spend less time on my computer, not more time. Since March, I am working from home (like many people in COVID time). It means I am no longer going outside of my house every day, I can spend sometime 4 hours straight without getting up, and after work I also spend time on my computer for personal endeavour. This means I am spending a huge amount of time in the day at the same place,without moving much. This one is difficult to balance, for now I think I will replace watching random videos on Youtube by writing for my blog but if I want to stay in good shape in the long run, I need to find a way to move more while working, or write somewhere else than the computer. Maybe a dictaphone? Handwriting is good but too slow and I still need to write it down in a digital form afterward so not so good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I plan to write some articles in French. For now it&amp;rsquo;s really difficult for me to write on technical topics even so it is my mother tongue because it always feels weird to have half the vocabulary in French and half in English. Even weirder is translating everything in French, because it becomes really hard to follow. In real-life nobody uses only French terms (in France at least, in Quebec, French is a bit more used for software jargon).
To help me overcome this difficulty, I will use &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitoduc.fr/&#34;&gt;bitoduc&lt;/a&gt;, an English-French dictionary of software terms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;let-the-fun-begin-&#34;&gt;Let the fun begin :)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NaNoWriMo started November first, this was the first article of a hopefully long series! I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward for this month and I really like the idea of bursting through a short period of time, with the help and motivation of the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you ever dreamed of writing, be it for a novel, a blog, poetry&amp;hellip; or anything really, join me :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;bonus-1&#34;&gt;Bonus 1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While daydreaming about how I would go on about doing NaNoWrimo and my old dreams of being a writer, I found a couple interesting link for writing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=24849485&#34;&gt;To write better, develop a habit of writing&lt;/a&gt; A HN thread about &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookpub.club/post/to-write-better-you-need-to-develop-a-habit-of-writing--1603298302647x354487348376371200&#34;&gt;this eponym article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.chrismytton.com/be-prolific/?&#34;&gt;Be prolific&lt;/a&gt; stating that quantity and quality goes hand in hand. The more you produce, the more you progress. The story in the article was actually debunked in many threads in HN or Reddit for having no real source, but I think the meaning being all of it stay true. In my case, if I never write anything in the hope of writing the perfect story the first time I try, it will be a lot less interesting than if I wrote lots of essays to train and grow a style.
I think a caveat here is that producing too much can lead to &lt;em&gt;brain diarrhea&lt;/em&gt;. If you just write everything that goes through your head, quality can be quite low. As always, you must find a balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in general, writing a lot is beneficial compared to writing very little when you want to improve your writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;bonus-2&#34;&gt;Bonus 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put in my NaNoWriMo profile that one of my all-time favourite books was Philip Pullman&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/His_Dark_Materials&#34;&gt;His Dark Materials&lt;/a&gt;. But to add it to my list, I had to find the title in English and it&amp;rsquo;s a lot different than in French. I spent some time in the Wikipedia page for it to try to understand why and discovered that one of the major sources of inspiration for this trilogy was John Milton&amp;rsquo;s Paradise Lost. I have reserved a copy already from my local library, I&amp;rsquo;ll have it in 10 days :) I still don&amp;rsquo;t have a good idea for why the name is quite different from one language to another, though :/&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>	